# Mhd Saria Allahham

🛘 13433336614 | @ sarea.laham@gmail.com | 🖬 LinkedIn | 🗘 Website | 😵 Google Scholar | 🕈 Montreal, QC

# Summary

I am an AI/ML Research Engineer with more than 4 years of experience in AI and research, and a strong background in telecommunications systems and engineering. My experience spans the development, fine-tuning, and deployment of Large Language Models (LLMs), Generative AI, Computer Vision models, Data Science, and MLOps. I spent a year and a half working for Samsung Research America, AI Center in Montreal, engaging in a variety of projects for wireless communications, indoor human-state estimation and localization, home automation, and LLMs. A proven track record in both academic research and industry projects demonstrates my capacity to bridge the gap between theoretical AI/ML research and real-world applications.

## EDUCATION

Queen's University

Kingston, ON, Canada

M.Sc. in Computer Science; GPA: 4.30/4.30

Jan 2021 - Apr 2022

Thesis: Multi-Orchestrator Mobile Edge Learning: Designing Energy-Efficient Task Allocation and Incentive Schemes

Qatar University

Doha, Qatar

B.Sc. in Computer Engineering GPA: 3.90/4.00

Jan 2016 - Apr 2020

Graduated with High Order of Excellence

Senior Project: Designing a Smart Home Controller for Smart Home Devices using Hand Gestures

## Job Experience

# Samsung Research America, AI Center

Montreal, QC, Canada

AI/ML Research Engineer

Oct 2022 - Feb 2024

- Developing, deploying, and testing AI algorithms on real hardware and simulations
- Leveraging the deep research work and findings to develop and program integrated software algorithms to solve real-world problems
- Translating mathematical and algorithmic problem specifications into efficient deployable code.
- Developing and proposing new project ideas.
- Writing scientific papers for publication and patents.
- Engaging with Samsung business units to develop new ideas that can have business impact.

#### Queen's University, School of Computing

Kingston, ON, Canada

Graduate Research Fellow

Jan 2021 - Sep 2022, Part-time

- Modeling and analyzing Federated Learning at the network edge for resource-limited smart devices.
- Developing energy-efficient protocols for Federated Learning.
- Writing and reviewing research articles.

### Qatar's University, Computer Science and Engineering Dep.

Doha, Qatar

Research Assistant

May 2020 - Sep 2021, Full-time

- Designing and implementing smart protocols using AI for Ultra Reliable Low Latency Communication (URLLC) in smart health systems.
- Reviewing and employing state-of-the-art smart algorithms for protocols.
- Writing and reviewing research articles.

#### Local 3GPP Chat

Self-developed

- Summary: A chatbot powered by Retrieval Augmented Generation (RAG) and a local LLM that gives information about ETSI and 3GPP standards.
- Programming Languages: Python
- Relevant Software & Libraries: PyTorch, Ollama, llama index, Transformers
- Open-source version: https://github.com/saria-lh/3GPP-RAG-chat

## 5G Mobile Wireless Networks Simulator with AI-based Load Balancing Algorithms

Samsung Research America

- Summary: A proprietary practical simulation software designed to simulate 5G Networks and AI load balancing algorithms.
- Programming Languages: Java, Python, MATLAB
- Relevant Software & Libraries: PyTorch, CVX/CVXPY, Stable Baselines3
- Open-source version: https://github.com/saria-lh/MERLIN

## AI-based Indoor Localization and Human State Estimation using Ultra-Wideband Protocol

Samsung Research America

- Summary: A proprietary framework that enables the estimation of location, activities, and the number of people in an indoor environment without requiring them to carry specific devices.
- Programming Languages: C/C++, Python, Java
- Relevant Software & Libraries: PyTorch, OpenCV, ROS, Docker

#### Skills & Expertise

# Software Development

- Programming Languages: Python, MATLAB, C/C++, Java, and Bash scripting
- Machine Learning and Data Science: SciPy, Pandas, NumPy, SciKit-Learn, Pandas, XGBoost, Matplotlib and Seaborn.
- Deep Learning: PyTorch, Tensorflow/Keras, and OpenCV.
- MLOps: LightningAI, Weights & Biases, and Azure ML
- Docker

#### **Artificial Intelligence**

- Data Science and Machine Learning.
- Deep Learning.
- Computer Vision.
- Natural Language Processing (NLP).
- Large Language Models (LLMs).
- Reinforcement Learning.
- Multi-Agent Systems.

#### Telecommunications and Computer Networks

- Digital Signal Processing.
- Edge networks.
- Internet of Things (IoT).
- TCP/IP network stack.
- Wireless and Cellular Networks.
- Reading 3GPP standards and implementing functionalities.
- Digital twins, simulation and experimental analysis for telecommunication systems.

- [1] Alaa Awad Abdellatif, **Allahham, Mhd Saria**, Noor Khial, Amr Mohamed, Aiman Erbad, and Khaled Shaban. Reliable federated learning for age sensitive mobile edge computing systems. In *ICC 2023-IEEE International Conference on Communications*, pages 1622–1627. IEEE, 2023.
- [2] Alaa Awad Abdellatif, **Allahham, Mhd Saria**, Amr Mohamed, Aiman Erbad, and Mohsen Guizani. Onsra: An optimal network selection and resource allocation framework in multi-rat systems. In *ICC 2021-IEEE International Conference on Communications*, pages 1–6. IEEE, 2021.
- [3] Emna Baccour, **Allahham, Mhd Saria**, Aiman Erbad, Amr Mohamed, Ahmed Refaey Hussein, and Mounir Hamdi. Zero touch realization of pervasive artificial intelligence as a service in 6g networks. *IEEE Communications Magazine*, 61(2):110–116, 2023.
- [4] Yahuza Bello, Alaa Awad Abdellatif, Allahham, Mhd Saria, Ahmed Refaey Hussein, Aiman Erbad, Amr Mohamed, and Mohsen Guizani. B5g: Predictive container auto-scaling for cellular evolved packet core. IEEE Access, 9:158204–158214, 2021.
- [5] Heba DM Dawoud, **Allahham, Mhd Saria**, Alaa Awad Abdellatif, Amr Mohamed, Aiman Erbad, and Mohsen Guizani. Patient-driven network selection in multi-rat health systems using deep reinforcement learning. In 2021 IEEE Global Communications Conference (GLOBECOM), pages 1–6. IEEE, 2021.
- [6] Naram Mhaisen, **Allahham**, **Mhd Saria**, Amr Mohamed, Aiman Erbad, and Mohsen Guizani. On designing smart agents for service provisioning in blockchain-powered systems. *IEEE Transactions on Network Science and Engineering*, 9(2):401–415, 2021.
- [7] Hassan Saadat, **Allahham, Mhd Saria**, Alaa Awad Abdellatif, Aiman Erbad, and Amr Mohamed. Rlassisted energy-aware user-edge association for iot-based hierarchical federated learning. In 2022 International Wireless Communications and Mobile Computing (IWCMC), pages 548–553. IEEE, 2022.
- [8] **Al Laham, Saria**, Bobak H Baghi, Pierre-Yves Lajoie, Amal Feriani, Sachini Herath, Steve Liu, and Gregory Dudek. Device-free human state estimation using uwb multi-static radios. arXiv preprint arXiv:2401.05410, 2023.
- [9] Al Lahham, Saria, Di Wu, Ekram Hossain, Xue Liu, and Gregory Dudek. Probabilistic mobility load balancing for multi-band 5g and beyond networks. arXiv preprint arXiv:2401.13792, 2024.
- [10] Allahham, Mhd Saria, Alaa Awad Abdellatif, Naram Mhaisen, Amr Mohamed, Aiman Erbad, and Mohsen Guizani. Multi-agent reinforcement learning for network selection and resource allocation in heterogeneous multi-rat networks. *IEEE Transactions on Cognitive Communications and Networking*, 8(2):1287–1300, 2022.
- [11] Allahham, Mhd Saria, Alaa Awad Abdellatif, Amr Mohamed, Aiman Erbad, Elias Yaacoub, and Mohsen Guizani. I-see: Intelligent, secure, and energy-efficient techniques for medical data transmission using deep reinforcement learning. *IEEE Internet of Things Journal*, 8(8):6454–6468, 2020.
- [12] Allahham, Mhd Saria, Mohammad F Al-Sa'd, Abdulla Al-Ali, Amr Mohamed, Tamer Khattab, and Aiman Erbad. Dronerf dataset: A dataset of drones for rf-based detection, classification and identification. *Data in brief*, 26:104313, 2019.
- [13] Allahham, Mhd Saria, Tamer Khattab, and Amr Mohamed. Deep learning for rf-based drone detection and identification: A multi-channel 1-d convolutional neural networks approach. In 2020 IEEE International Conference on Informatics, IoT, and Enabling Technologies (ICIoT), pages 112–117. IEEE, 2020.
- [14] **Allahham, Mhd Saria**, Amr Mohamed, Aiman Erbad, and Mohsen Guizani. Motivating learners in multi-orchestrator mobile edge learning: A stackelberg game approach. *IEEE Canadian Journal of Electrical and Computer Engineering*, 46(1):69–76, 2022.

- [15] Allahham, Mhd Saria, Amr Mohamed, Aiman Erbad, and Hossam Hassanein. On the modeling of reliability in extreme edge computing systems. In 2022 5th International Conference on Communications, Signal Processing, and their Applications (ICCSPA), pages 1–6. IEEE, 2022.
- [16] Allahham, Mhd Saria, Amr Mohamed, and Hossam Hassanein. Incentive-based resource allocation for mobile edge learning. In 2022 IEEE 47th Conference on Local Computer Networks (LCN), pages 157–164. IEEE, 2022.
- [17] **Allahham, Mhd Saria**, Sameh Sorour, Amr Mohamed, Aiman Erbad, and Mohsen Guizani. Energy-efficient multi-orchestrator mobile edge learning. arXiv preprint arXiv:2109.00757, 2021.